Meichan Huang, Ph.D., Data Scientist

Dallas Fort-Worth, TX, 75428 | 903.274.7863 | meichan.huangg@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/meichanhuang/ | https://github.com/mhgarrett

CAREER OBJECTIVE

A detailed-oriented, teamwork-oriented, and data-driven problem-solver with 7+ years' experience conducting data analysis and research projects. Knowledge in machine learning algorisms, NLP, statistics, data extraction and wrangling, data analysis, data modeling, and data visualization. Worked on projects that involve quantitative and qualitative analysis, e.g. testing and performance data, client record management, and natural language modeling. Trained researcher with strong decision-making and project-management skills.

EDUCATION

Syracuse University
M.S. in Applied Data Science

January 2022 - May 2024

M.S. in Applied Data Science 4.0 GPA

Texas A&M University - Commerce Commerce, TX

Ph.D. in English (Applied Linguistics)

August 2019

Edinburgh University Edinburgh, UK

M.S. in TESOL November 2011

Sichuan International Studies University

Chongqing, China

B.A. in Translation and Interpretation

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Faires & Garrett Law Firm Commerce, TX

Data Analyst (Contractor)

May 2022 - Present

July 2010

- Design and manage relational databases of law office clients with Microsoft Access, effectively utilizing SQL codes to query client data and generate case reports, increase information retrieval efficiency and support paralegals' work
- Extract, transform, and analyze operational cost data, create performance metrics for cases, output reports using Excel Power Pivot
- Research public data sources as applicable to project needs such as property tax protests and corporal tax filing, and help clients successfully contest and reduce the property tax rate under the guidance of the lawyer

Department of Languages, Literatures, and Linguistics, Syracuse University

Syracuse, NY

Assistant Program Coordinator of ESOL Program

June 2021 – August 2023

- Coordinate ESOL placement tests, collect and analyze placement results to accurately determine over 1000 incoming international students' language performance and align with composition course/training requirements
- Manage a 10k-entries international student record relational database and monitor student registration using Excel conditional functions
- Query student registration information in ESOL courses across databases using Excel
- Build dashboards to monitor student enrollment numbers and provide projections using Excel Power Pivot for course scheduling purposes
- Provide technical leadership in coordinating course scheduling and offering and faculty teaching resource allocation

Department of Languages and Literature, Texas A & M University - Commerce

Commerce, TX

Linguistic Researcher

September 2013 - August 2019

- Adapted analytical skills to research projects using SPSS and Excel spreadsheets, provided data modeling, and generated 6 referred publications peer-reviewed journals, and 20 prestigious international conferences presentations
- Led a research project on speech perception and recognition, receiving \$2250 research grant from The International Research Fund for Teaching (TIRF)
- Collected research data from second language English speakers to create phonological profiles (spectrograms) using Praat and Computerized Speech Lab and ran Principal Component Analysis and Regression models on the dataset
- Curated a 5-hour Chinese dyadic humor dataset and generated 2 conference publications

• Managed 10-million-word Augmented and Alternative Communication (AAC) Corpus, supervised student workers, verified accuracy of student time entry and oversaw student workers' task performance

Department of Languages, Literatures, and Linguistics, Syracuse University

Syracuse, NY

Assistant Teaching Professor & Researcher

September 2019 - Present

- Create engaging lectures, activities, and assessments for undergraduate and graduate-level students on writing and speaking skills for academic purposes 4 times per week
- Conduct research on L2 writing and speaking production using corpus linguistics approach
- Maintain updated reports on student progress and intervened if behavioral or academic abnormalities occur
- Compose letters of recommendation for students pursuing graduate schools and transferring to other universities

PROJECTS

Project 1: Wine reviews: Exploratory Analysis and Text Classification

- Performed data wrangling (imputing, removing missing values, text data preprocessing) and exploratory analysis (data visualization, pivot tables, word cloud) on 200k data entries
- Conducted data analysis using various machine learning models to examine the accuracy of a model to predict wine price, including naïve bayes text classification and SVM classification
- Data analysis tools: Python (pandas, numpy, sklearn, and NLTK)

Project 2: Relational Database for Student Records

- Compile the data to construct a relational database for student record retrieval, maintain and update database, and query necessary information for program coordination duties and for teaching faculty hiring purposes
- Data analysis tools: mySQL, Excel (pivot tables, conditional formatting, count if)

Project 3: Semantic components of laughter behavior: a lexical field study of 14 translations of one flew over the Cuckoo's nest.

- Data analysis for the Chinese version translation
- Outcome: a publication in the peer-editing journal of Humor: International Journal of Humor Research
- Link to the project: https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/humor-2022-0114/html

Project 4: The role of suprasegmental features on the speech perception and production of World English speakers

- Primary investigator
- Received \$2250 research grant from The International Research Fund for Teaching (TIRF)
- Published a book chapter by Routledge, a book manuscript under commission by Lexington Books, and 3 prestigious international conference presentations
- Performed principal component analysis and stepwise regression analysis using R; used Praat for data annotation and labeling

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Gironzetti, E., Hempelmann, C., Dawsari, A., Balali, S., Chlopicki, W., Huang, M., Laineste, L., Menjo, S., & Shilikhina, K. (2023). Semantic Components of Laughter Behavior: A Lexical Field Study of 14 Translations of One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest. Humor. 36(1), 95-133. https://doi.org/10.1515/humor-2022-0114

Gironzetti, E., Pickering, L., **Huang, M.,** Zhang, Y., Menjo, S., & Attardo, S. (2016). Smiling synchronicity and gaze patterns in dyadic humorous conversations. *Humor*, 29(2), 301-324.

SKILLS

Data analysis and wrangling

Data visualization

Machine Learning Algorithms

Relational database management

Statistics and quantitative analysis

Qualitative analysis

R (caret, ggplot)

mySQL Tableau

Python: Pandas, Numpy, NLTK, Sklearn, Seaborn,

Matlibplot, BeautifulSoup

MongoDB

Microsoft Suite: Excel, PowerPoint, Word, Access

LANGUAGES

- Mandarin Chinese (Native): native reading, writing, and listening language; conduct research
- English (Near-Native): Dominant and instructional language in the working and daily settings; research on the syntax and phonology of English